Inventory to the John Nicholas Beffel Papers TAM.055
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
John Nicholas Beffel Papers
1909-1970
TAM.055
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
15.5 linear feet (32 boxes)
John Nicholas Beffel (1887 1973) was a radical journalist, publicist, and editor. A prolific writer of articles, essays, and publicity dealing with leftist issues, many pertained to the syndicalist labor organization the Industrial Workers of the World (IWW), anarchism and several noted anarchists (he edited several works by or about them). Beffel also produced short stories, autobiographical sketches and poems. Much of his activity involved defense committees for radicals either prosecuted either for their beliefs or for activity related thereto. The collection contains correspondence, subject files, writings by Beffel and others, (unprocessed) Family Files, and an unprocessed Addundum.
Beffel, John Nicholas
Box 1-32
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions. However, there may be preservation concerns in relation to the two unprocessed series (V. Family Files; VII. Addendum) that may limit access.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in eight series: I. Correspondence; II. Subject Files; III. Writings by Beffel; IV, Writings by Others; V. Family Files (unprocessed); Series VI: User photocopies from Series IV (Writings by Others); Series VII, Addendum (unprocessed); "Series" VIII: Index to Correspondents. Folder level control for series I, Correspondence; box level control for the remaining series.
Historical/Biographical Note
John Nicholas Beffel (1887 1973) Radical journalist, publicist, and editor. A prolific writer of articles, essays, and publicity dealing with leftist issues, many pertaining to the syndicalist labor organization the Industrial Workers of the World (IWW), anarchism and several noted anarchists. Beffel also produced short stories, autobiographical sketches and poems. Much of his activity involved defense committees for accused radicals in such cases as: the Mooney Billings Case in which the two men were found guilty of a fatal bombing during a Preparedness Day parade in San Francisco in 1916; the Centralia, Washington, case in which ten IWW's were accused of murder during an assault of IWW headquarters in connection with an Armistice Day parade in 1919; Sacco and Vanzetti; the Kentucky Miners Defense, stemming from the bloody “Battle of Evarts” in Harlan County, 1931; the case of Athos Terzani, an anti fascist accused of accidentally murdering a comrade during a fascist rally in New York in 1933; and the un¬solved political murder of anti fascist leader Carlo Tresca in 1943. Beffel was also involved with The League for Mutual Aid, a social service agency for leftists in need of assistance, founded by Roger Baldwin in 1920. Much of the boxes of correspondence relates to Beffel’s organizational and publicity efforts in these causes; much of the rest concerns his writings or those of his correspondents. Beffel edited several (published and unpblished) manuscripts, primarily by or about various anarchists (including Mikhail Bakunin, Rose Pesotta, and Harry Kelley, co-founder of the Ferrer colony in Stelton, N.J.), was interested in, and wrote about mysterious disappearances, and sometimes wrote articles under the names of Lancey Fitzgibbons, George Moresby, Mary Starland, Daniel Tower and others.
Scope and Contents note
The papers contain correspondence, subject fifles, writings (by Beffel and others), Family files (unprocessed), an Index to Series I, Correspondence, and an unprocessed Addendum. Correspondents include Richard Brazier, Ralph Chaplin, Daniel Eisenberg, Aldino Felicani, Covington Hall, Harvey O'Connor, Rose Pesotta, Anna Roy, Vincent Starrett, Fred Thompson, Wilma Haywood Veleker, Albert Wehde, Art Young, and numerous family members. Note that correspondence is also found throughout the subject files. Series II, Subject Files, chiefly relate to Beffel's organizational and publicity efforts in the defense of accused radicals in the Mooney-Billings case, Centralia, Wash.; a case involving members of the Industrial Workers of the World (WW); the Sacco-Vanzetti case; the Kentucky miners' defense in Harlan County (1931); the case of Athos Terzani; and Beffel's involvement with the League for Mutual Aid, a social service agency for leftists. The two Writings series contain manuscripts of writings by Beffel and others, including Bakunin's Political Philosophy: His Writings on Scientific Anarchism, edited by Beffel; several chapters from Rose Pesotta's Bread Upon the Waters (1944), edited by Beffel and Days of Our Lives (1958), both before editorial changes; unpublished autobiographies by Harry Kelly (co-founder of the Ferrer colony in Stelton, N.J.)and Enness Ellae (IWW member); published and unpublished articles and essays, most about labor and leftist personalities and issues; and stories, poems, reviews, and autobiographical pieces on Beffel's boyhood in Seneca, Ill. and notes for a book. Although preoccupied with leftist causes, Beffel manifested a deep interest in his writings in mysterious disappearances; notes for a book on the subject is found here under the title "Where Did These Men Die?"
NOTE: There is an Index to Correspondents ("Series" VIII) at the end of the container list. This Index references correspondents represented in more than one location in the collection, and in particular, correspondents represented in Series II, Subjects. Conversely,the SEE and SEE ALSO references found in Series II, Subjects, refer researchers to additional correspondence by the individuals in question to be found in Series I, Correspondence, for which there is a folder level container list.
FOR ADDITIONAL INQUIRIES, CONTACT: peter.filardo@nyu.edu.
Provenance
Gift of John Beffel via Robert Colase, 1972.
Baldwin, Roger Nash, 1884-1981; Beffel, John Nicholas; Billings, Warren K., 1893-1972; Bluestein, Abe; Chaplin, Ralph, 1887-1961; Eisenberg, Daniel; Ellae, Enness; Feliciani, Aldino, 1891-1967; Fitzgibbons, Lancey; Gandhi, Mahatma, 1869-1948; Hall, Covington, 1871-1951; Industrial Workers of the World.; Kelly, Harry; Kentucky Miners Defense.; League for Mutual Aid (U.S.).; Modern School (Stelton, N.J.).; Mooney, Thomas J., 1882-1942.; Moresby, George; O'Connor, Harvey, 1897-1987.; Pesotta, Rose, 1896-; Rocker, Rudolf, 1873-1958.; Roy, Anna; Starrett, Mary; Starrett, Vincent, 1886-1974; Terzani, Athos; Thompson, Fred, 1900-1987; Tresca, Carlo, 1879-1943.; Wehde, Albert; Young, Art, 1866-1943.; Anarchists |v Biography.; Anarchists.; Autobiographies.; Evarts (Ky.); Harlan County (Ky.); Manuscripts (document genre); Reviews (document genre); Right and left (Political science); Sacco-Vanzetti Trial, Dedham, Mass., 1921.; Stelton (N.J.); Syndicalism |z United States.; Syndicalists |z United States.
- Series I: Correspondence. NOTE: See also the Index to Correspondents found at the end of the Container List (after Series VII)., 1900-; 4.5 linear feet 9 boxes
  - A, 1910-1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Appel, Paul, 1924-1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - B, 1921-1968, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brazier, Richard, 1924-1968, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Buckley, John, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Burr, Jane, 1918-1957, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - C, 1911-1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Campbell, Agnes H. (includes photograph), undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Campbell, Agnes H., undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Campbell, Agnes H., 1922 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Campbell, Agnes H., 1923 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Campbell, Agnes H., 1923 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Campbell, Agnes H., 1924 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Campbell, Agnes H., 1924 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Campbell, Agnes H., 1924 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Campbell, Agnes H., 1925 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Campbell, Agnes H. (includes photographs), 1925 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Campbell, Agnes H., 1926 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Campbell, Agnes H., 1927 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Campbell, Agnes H., 1928 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Campbell, Agnes H., 1929 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Campbell, Agnes H., 1930 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Campbell, Agnes H., 1931 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Campbell, Agnes H., 1932, 1937-1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Campbell, Agnes H. (from Various People), 1924-1925 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Carey, Eugene F., 1947, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Cascaden, Gordon, 1935-1936, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Chamberlain, Grace Ann, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Carson, Saul and Betty, 1937-1966, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Chamberlain, Grace Anne (includes photograph), 1920-1921 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Chamberlain, Grace Anne, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Chamberlain, Grace Anne, 1940-1960 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Chamberlain, Grace Anne: Various Book Chapters and REsearch Clippings for Unpublished Book "When You Visit the Sick", 1937-1940 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Chaplin, Ralph, 1923-1937, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Clinton, Sackville H.M., 1937-1967, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Clinton, Sackville H.M., 1962-1965 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Clinton, Sackville H.M., 1966 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Clinton, Sackville H.M., 1967 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Clinton, Sackville H.M., 1968 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Clinton, Sackville H.M., 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Comfort, Will Levington, 1910-1912, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - D, 1910-1970 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Davin, Tom, 1937-1941 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Diggins, John P., 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Dillion, Mary, 1914-1920, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Dreiser, Theodore, 1914-1932 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - E, 1924-1969, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Eisenberg, Daniel, 1938-1961, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Eisenberg, Daniel (with Farrar and Rinehart Publishers, 1938-1944 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Eisenberg, Daniel (Memorandums, etc. by JNB: RE: I Find the Missing), 1938, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Eisenberg, Daniel (Beffel Correspondence RE: I Find the Missing), 1937-1938 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Eisenberg, Daniel (Miscellaneous Publicity and Reviews, Etc.), 1938, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - F, 1918-1966, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Felicani, Aldino and Ateo, 1947-1970, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Fletcher, Ben, 1967-1969 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Fresco, Mauricio, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Fuessle, Helen, 1925-1926 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Fuller, Torrey, 1932-1961, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Furman, Lee, 1937-1941 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - G, 1919-1966, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Gawthorpe, Mary (Sanders), 1938-1964 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Gehrig, Gladys Bell (includes photographs), 1925-1929, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - H (includes photograph), 1912-1970, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - H (Hodgins?), K., 1924-1940 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Hall, Covington, 1937-1950 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Hapgood, Mary Donovan, 1964-1969 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Hilson, Maxine, 1934-1940 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Humphrey, Mary, 1925-1938, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - I, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Inalis, Agnes, 1936-1967 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - J, 1919-1968, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Jarrett, Ida, 1965-1968 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - K, 1923-1966 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Karsner, David, 1918-1932, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Karsten, Helen Ward Tippy, 1921-1967, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Keller, Carl, 1925-1969 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Kenderdine, John D., 1925-1966, undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Kitchen, Irene, 1960-1969 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - L, 1911-1967, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Lonergan, Hella and Warren, 1933-1968 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Luchkovsky, Lisa, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Luchkovsky, Lisa, 1960-1967 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Lyla, 1938-1942 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - M, 1909-1969, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Mahler, Herbert, 1937-1961 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - McSwigan, Marie, 1935-1940 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Mencken, H.L., 1914-1938 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous, 1911-1966, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - RE: Mooney, Tom, 1920-1931 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - N, 1934-1969 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Naretty, Vera, 1938-1966 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Nomad, Max, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - O, 1916-1966, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - O'Connor, Harvey, 1926-1969 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - O'Connor, Tom, 1939 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - O'Connor, Tom, 1960-1961 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - O'Conner, Tom, 1961-1966 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - P, 1930-1951 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Pesotta, Rose, 1949-1965 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Pesotta, Rose: "Bread Upon the Waters" Book Manuscript (Different from the Published Book), undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Pesotta, Rose (Typescript "Days of Our Lives" Probably Chpater 12 of Sweetheart of the Army), 1952 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Price, Burr, 1910-1940 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Q, 1934 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - R, 1913-1966 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Roy, Anna (Includes Manuscript for Unpublished Book Chapter), 1969 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - S, 1907-1969, undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - S, Laura, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Sandberg, Carl, 1920-1966 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Sheehan, Lucy and Bill, 1925-1939 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Shields, Art and Ester, 1920-1969 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Schulkind, Adelaide, 1930-1970 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Sinclair, Upton, 1920-1967 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Spivak, John L. (AKA Jack), 1965-1968 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Scarlett, Vincent, 1918-1967 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - T, 1910-1967 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Teichner, Miriam, 1914-1928 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Thomas, Norman, 1936-1968 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Thompson, Fred (RE: Joe Hill), 1947-1967 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Travaglio, Esther Hartz, 1926-1970 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Tresca, Carlo, 1944-1969 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Trunck, Irene, 1939-1949 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - U, 1928 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - V, 1919 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - RE: Valenti, Girolamo (Obituary), 1966-1967 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Veleker, Wilma Haywood, 1962-1968 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - W, 1910-1969 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - W, Margaret, 1936-1952 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Walling, Anna Struncky, 1916-1970 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Wehde, Albert, 1923-1926 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Wehde, Albert, 1927-1941 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Wehde, Albert (Wehde Letters with Others than Beffel), 1923-1931, undated (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Wehde, Albert: RE: Book Fingerprints Can Be Forged (Includes Manuscript Drafts and Reviews), 1925-1938 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Wehde, Albert: RE: Book Fingerprints Can Be Forged (Promotional Materials from Tremonia Publishing Co.), 1923-1926, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Wehde, Albert: RE: Fingerprints Can Be Forged and Since Leaving Home (Letters by Beffel and Others), 1922-1937, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Wehde, Albert: RE: Fingerprints Can Be forged and Since Leaving Home (Letters To/From Various People), 1923-1936, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Wehde, Albert: RE: Book Since Leaving Home (Includes Partial Manuscript and Notes), 1923, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Wehde, Albert: RE: Since Leaving Home (Includes Biographical Materials about Wehde), 1923-1931, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Wehde, Albert: RE: Book Since Leaving Home Corrections and Mailing Lists, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Wehde, Albert: Reviews of Since Leaving Home, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Wehde, Albert: Related Drawings and Photographs (includes original sketches), undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Worthington, Dorothy, 1932-1968, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Y, 1925 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Young, Art, 1920-1936 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Young, Art, 1937-1938 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Young, Art, 1939-1943, undated (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Young, Art (Letters To and From Art Young), 1916-1966 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - RE: Art Young, 1933-1966 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Z, 1926 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Zimmerman, Mary (includes photograph), 1930-1965 (Box 9, Folder 17)
- Series II: Subjects
  - Subject Files (Box 10)
    General note
    AMERICAN CIVIL LIBERTIES UNION, Beffel memorandum to A.C.L.U., 1931
    BROTHERHOOD OF UTILITY EMPLOYEES OF AMERICA, BROOKLYN LOCAL No. 102, RE: Brooklyn Edison Company 1934 35, 1939
    CENTRALIA (12 Folders):
    Affidavits (photostats)
    Correspondence: No. 1: 1920, 1922-1924, undated,
    Correspondence No. 2: 1925-1926, 1932
    Mailing lists
    Miscellaneous
    Newspaper clippings (4 Folders)
    Printed material re: Centralia
    Review bv Beffel of The American Legion Story by Moley, Jr.
    Statement and articles
    ( See Also: BRAZIERY Richard; CHAPLIN, Ralph; O'CONNOR, Harvey; SHEEHAN, Bill and Lucy; SULGROVE, Leslie B.)
    CHICAGO DAILY NEWS
    COLONIAL TIMES (See: LONGERAN, Nell and Warren; Writing Non fiction (Billington and Colonial families)
    CONFEDERATED SPANISH SOCIETIES (Espana Libre)
    (7) CONTRACT PRISON LABOR
    (8) CONTROCORRENTE – MEMORIAL ISSUE (3 Folders): Articles, Correspondence with Ateo Felicani, Correspondence, General
    (9) CONVICTION OF INNOCENT PEOPLE
    (10) CREMATION (See: EVANS, Ernestine)
  - Contains: (Box 11)
    DRAFT RIOTS CIVIL WAR; "ELEPHANTS AND IRISMEN,” A vaudeville type act put on by Beffel at various times
    FEDERATED PRESS Correspondence, 1921
    FERRER SCHOOL: Correspondence re: Harry Kelly book and research by various people on Kelly and the Ferrer School; also "A Tribute to Harry Kelly" by Abe Bluestein, given at the Rand School, 1953
    SUHR, Richard Ford and Herman Suhr Case, 1913-1914, re: Wheatland, California riot during the hop pickers strike
    INDUSTRIAL WORIMS OF THE WORLD, Includes: "An Open Letter to President Harding – General Defense Committee, 1922 ?"
    "Who Were the Wobblies?" by Westbrook Pegler
    “Concerning the lynching of Wesly Everest and Frank Little" a statement by Beffel
    JOBS AND JOB-HUNTING: Includes letter to and from various editors, etc. about inquiries made by Beffel about positions available
    KENTUCKY MINERS DEFENSE (2 folders): Correspondence, 1937 – 39; Statements and articles
    LEAGUE FOR MUTUAL AID (LFMA), 9 Folders: LFMA 1930s; LFMA 1940s; LFMA 1950s; LF14A 1960 – 63; Anniversary Dinner Celebration, 1969 – 70; LFMA Executive Committee; LFMA Executive Committee, Finances 1940s; LFMA History by Beffel
  - Contains: (Box 12)
    LIBRARIES: Letters generally pertaining to gifts given by Beffel to various libraries See Also: INGLIS, Agnes (pertaining to the Labadie Collection)
    MARY CELESTE: Material relating to the mysterious disappearance of the crew of the ship the Mary Celeste
    MENTAL ILLNESS Material about conditions in (state) mental institutions, including personal accounts by various people
    O.R.T.A. for Dem Com (Democratic Communications), See: Zapata, Modesto (in correspondence section)
    POSTAL WORKERS
    SACCO and VANZETTI (9 Folders):
    Notes, general items and correspondence (late 1960s) with Decker, Ann Folger; Ehrmann, Herbert B; Musmanno, Hon., Michael A.
    Printed material re: Sacco and Vanzetti
    Bibliographies
    Correspondence No. 1: 1921-1929, 1937 Correspondence No. 2: 1947, 1959–1970 Correspondence No. 3: Memorial, 1967 (Including press releases and articles)
    Re: Plays and musicals based on Sacco and Vanzetti
    Francis Russell's reply to Fred Cook re: Sacco and Vanzetti
    Gus Tyler's speech at the Sacco and Vanzetti Memorial
    See Also: APPEL, Paul; DONOVAN, Mary (Hapgood); DOUGLAS, Hon. William O.; HUNTINGTON, Catherine; MOORE., Fred H.; O'CONNOR, Tom; SHIELDS, Art and Esther; THOMAS Norman.
  - Contains: (Box 13)
    TERZANI CASE (4 Folders): Affidavits; Correspondence, 1933 – 34; Newspaper clippings; Press releases, Memorandum
    CARLO TRESCA (10 Folders):
    Tresca Memorial Committee:
    Correspondence No. 1: 1944 – 46
    Correspondence No. 2 1947 – 48,
    Correspondence No. 3 – 1949,
    Correspondence No. 4 – 1950,
    Correspondence No. 5 1952 – 53,
    Correspondence No. 6 with Hon. Frank Hogan, 1949—50
    Undated material:
    Draft of a pamphlet on Tresca, “Murder in the Dim out" by Beffel,
    Articles, miscellaneous
    Un American Activities Committee correspondence, 1949
    TUNNELS
    UNUEMPLOYED UNION OF NEW YORK – 1931
    UNITED LIBERTARIAN ORGANIZATION: Statements and correspondence of Walter Starrett, 1937
    UNITED OFFICE AND PROFESSIONAL WORKERS OF AMERICA, Including a Local 16 flier and one letter from "M" (Margaret)
    THE WEST
    RE: Writing -- Letters pertaining to Beffel's writing; compiled by name of magazine or publication
    MISCELLANEOUS MAILING LISTS
- Series III: Writings by Beffel
  - Contains: (Box 14)
    Short Stories (some published, 1912-1937):
    "The wanderer meets her at the edge of the wood," Nov. 6, 1912
    Altars of the Gods, November 16, 1912
    At the Foot of the Totem Pole, Dec. 13, 1923 (also entitled Never Go Back, May 6, 1935)
    The Boy Who cried Wolf, February 28, 1932
    The Camel Stealer, April 16, 1919
    Canines Met at Night
    The City of Tombs, October 24, 1912
    The Dance of Death, July 28, 1926
    The Deaths and the Lights, July 22, 1933
    Demetri, October 5, 1912
    Denmark, October 21, 1912
    Dog in the Night, September 29, 1927
    Dogs Met at Night, October 16, 1933?
    Empire Stuff (also entitled McIntyre Puts It Over) 1919?
    Fantasia
    The Farm, May 12, 1912
    Fifty Minutes from Chicago
    Gas in Area D, October 15, 1927
    A Girl in Vermont (by John Strong (pseud.)
    Ghost House
    Glad Do I Die, July 3, 1913
    Grid Patton's Dog, March 27, 1912
    Hard Sledding, April 2, 1937
    Helping Ed, February 25, 1916
    I Find a Dog (also a different version entitled Lost Dog)
    "It was a Son She Heard From Her Father's Ship..."
    The Laughter of Fairies, August 13, 1912
    Light in the Sky, November 30, 1914
    The Man Near the Stove, September 7, 1929 (also entitled They Don't Mix)
    The Man With the Black Wiskers: 3 different verions, one dated November 9, 1923
    Mean Man Mallory, January 17, 1924
    Mean Man Mallory and the Goat
    Melody's End, August 7, 1934
    Mightier Than the Machine gun
    Miracles Even Now, September 9, 1927
    Moral of Australia; Muldoon, October 1, 1912
    The Night Clerk and the Gold, begun Jan. 17, 1926; resumed Aug.17, 1926
    On Thunder Bay (also entitled Joe Chenery)
    Open That Chest! (also entitled End of the Rope and The Brass Bound Chest)
    A Queen Come Back to Haunt Me
    The Scar, August 11, 1914
    Slatko the No Good (also entitled The Hole in the Earth)
    Some Upper Room
    Son of a Crimp, August 12, 1923
    The Soup Eater Silenced at Last, February 10, 1919?
    The Trained Duck (also entitled A Thief in the Wings) Sept. 24, 1934
    Up An Alley (also called Up an Alley in Ohio) June 29, 1927
    Up the Snow Slopes of Rainier
    The Viking Woman
    West From St. Paul by Mary Starland (pseud.)
    The Wild Wild West; Waterloo
    The Youngster in Buena Terra (retired copy).
  - Contains: (Box 15)
    "Annie Oakley" -- Includes 3 drafts of article on Annie Oakley, letters to various people concerning the article and notes by JNB on Annie Oakley
    "Burn, Black Man, Burn" -- Article written in 1943(?): Includes 3 copies of the article and notes by J"NB on that subject
    "Dark Day in New England" -- Article written for The Mercurv April 1943: Includes typescript of the article "Blackout in New England,” letters to Eugene Lyons and Robert Littell, and misc. material related to the article
    "The Fauntlerov Plague": Material and article relating to a proposed statue honoring Frances Hodgson Burnett, author of Little Lord Fauntleroy. (Beffel was opposed to the building of the statue)
    "Sir Martin Frobisher": Includes first draft and final (?) draft of articles on Frobisher, notes and newspaper clippings
    Mooney, Tom: Serials of newspaper articles on Mooney written in June 1920
    Radicals I have Met: Draft of the article "Four Radicals" which was published in The American Mercur April 1932, and Includes sketches of E.V. Debs, Bill Haywood, Vanzetti, Lucy Parsons and Tom Mooney (The last sketch was deleted from the final draft of the article)